all right everybody
welcome back i've got a very exciting
episode in store for you today i'm
sitting here with dr john verveiki
john thank you so much for being here
thank you eric for inviting me
so you have been on my radar for a while
after i was introduced through twitter
to the awakening from the meaning crisis
series
and subsequently inhaled all of that at
a very rapid pace
because it was a synthesis
of quite frankly a so much but b
synthesized so well and so clearly that
you know i really feel it should be
somewhere in the high school curriculum
to look at
you know with with that i think
part of the reason i really wanted to
have this conversation today is a just
introduce more people
to you to your ideas into your thinking
because it gives
i think most importantly it gives mental
frameworks
and it gives shared language so you can
start
digging in instead of just saying i
notice a lot of people in this space
saying
you know things are things are wrong
either inside or outside and i kind of
don't know why but i know it's
i know it's off a little bit and having
this language now just gives you
such strong tools uh to approach it
um so before we dive in because we have
a
we have a fair list to cover um can you
just give a bit of your background
how you got to doing what you're doing
today
oh sure um first of all eric thank you
for what you just said
i want you to know that and your
listeners to know that it means a great
deal to me
i i aspire to truly mean what i'm
about to say which is uh above and
beyond
being right about any particular claim
or any particular theory
providing people with you know
conceptual vocabulary and a theoretical
grammar so that they can articulate and
express
and reflect and communicate that is my
primary goal in everything i'm doing in
everything i'm doing so thank you for
saying that
it's much appreciated uh about me
um i don't know where would be the
appropriate thing to begin
i was brought up in a religious
framework fundamentalist christianity
that
uh with only over a period of about 25
years have i come into what i consider
a properly ambivalent uh attitude
towards it um
in that initially of course
um my attitude was because it was a very
traumatizing kind of
religious framework my attitude towards
it was a very antagonistic aggressive
atheistic rejection because of course it
had um
hurt me but um
your mother religion is like your mother
tongue uh you'll never
you may learn another language but you
you won't live in it the way you live
in your mother tongue right it's woven
into the very fabric of your coming into
being
and so that left
in me especially in the in the figure of
jesus of nazareth
it left in me a kind of hunger
for the depth
or at least what i perceived to be a
depth of life
and a depth of connectivity and a depth
of meaning
that i didn't i would probably say i
didn't experience
in that religion but that had been
portended for me
and so i carried that hunger around
and i um
i it sort of led me to as i said to
atheism and
a deep kind of nihilism
which is where in my sort of uh early
adulthood i encountered um
in a very inarticulate way and i'm sure
lots of people have this kind of
encounter
perhaps that's some of their resonance
with my work but
i encountered what you might call the
meeting crisis
individually in a very intense but
co-hate and searing but
almost inexpressible manner um
and so i i was wrestling with that and
um you know i was reading some young um
i would have been just introduced to
young by uh the fiction of
uh robertson davies and i was reading
some permanent hessa
i've been introduced to uh buddhism uh
that way
and then i got into university and i met
uh plato and the figure of socrates and
this had just
a titanic effect on me because
it gave me the sense
of a a palpable
sense of uh of moving towards that kind
of connection
and meaning that i had felt portended
in my religious heritage but had
actually not met and
and i i saw him figure in the figure of
socrates
an individual that of course i didn't
associate with that trauma because it
was
he was a new figure for me so i
immediately took up this project of the
cultivation
of wisdom you know in the sloppy way you
do
when you're an undergraduate um and and
that and that's not a criticism that's
how it should be done
and that's how it's inevitably done um
but what happened to me
is very quickly that the figure of
socrates the aspiration to
transcendence and to depth of meaning
and the cultivation of wisdom fall off
the academic table
and you don't talk about that anymore
you get all worried about epistemology
and skepticism and all this
very technical and argumentation and
i come to i came to value academic
philosophy for its own sake because i
i i found the tools it was affording me
and
and the stance of you know the meta
scientific critique and the metacultural
critique and the meta-historical
boutique i found that all very valuable
but
because of the way i got into it i also
was deeply dissatisfied
and so i undertook uh to
try and find um
another avenue for the cultivation of
wisdom
and deep connection and deep meaning
so i took up a bunch of i you know i
guess sort of inspired by herman hesse
you know i got involved with um eastern
wisdom practices and i was very
fortunate to be taught an ecology of
practices i was taught
the past meditation medic contemplation
tai chi chuan chi kung
as this integrated ecology that's that's
the that's the birthplace of the idea
of an ecology of practices and i i just
found the dynamics of that
powerful and transformative uh and in
ways i was
wasn't recognizing it i had i had
powerful moments where other people were
recognizing changes in me
before i recognized that and i saw this
um
and so two sort of streams were then
going on in my life this academic stream
uh and right and i got i finished my ma
in philosophy and i was just
the dissatisfaction just got too great
and by that time a new discipline that
opened up that incorporated philosophy
but also did
lots of psychology and artificial
intelligence and linguistics and
anthropology and that was cognitive
science so i went back
and did a specialist degree in cognitive
science to get into that
while continuing on in in all of these
um
you know uh embodiment practices that
within the ecology of practices and then
what about the time i was done
uh my cognitive science degree i started
teaching now because i had already done
philosophy i didn't have to do any
philosophy for my cog sci degree
so i ended up doing more psychology than
people do for their psychology degree
it was i was fully trained for doing
psychology
as well so i started teaching some
psychology courses and
an introductory cog sci course and at
about that time
cog sci had come to a place in
psychology
where you could start talking about some
of the things
that were right like wisdom
and mindfulness and self-transcendence
and mystical experience and suddenly
these two things that have been separate
came together uh for me
and then a a good friend and colleague
of mine
and somebody whose work i highly
recommend uh evan thompson was supposed
to teach a course on
buddhism and cogside that he couldn't do
it and so he recommended me
to teach it and i saw that i could bring
these two streams together to
because that's what the course was about
buddhism and cogside bringing
you know these two streams together and
then i thought
i could bring those together to address
this problem that
i've been wrestling on personally this
meaning crisis and so i did the course
and then that eventually evolved over
time into the series
and so this ongoing dialogue between
these
three figures within my psyche um
socrates and ultimately the way of
dialogues which hopefully we'll talk
about a bit today
the buddha and the way of mindfulness
you know mystical experience
self transcendence and then i i was able
through them to return back to jesus
and also the importance of dear logos
because he has
he had he is also a midwife of others
and
and there again the return to agape as a
fundamental
way of life and that i could see that
because i could understand it from the
buddhist notion of compassion
and so all these things uh came together
with me with this new emerging and
increasingly
powerful form of cognitive science um
and so that's how i got where i am
that's how i
am the the person i am
and that is why i'm engaged in the
project that i'm engaged in
wow so if that wasn't enough of a
trailer to start watching the meeting
crisis i don't know what is
because that is fantastic i was actually
talking to a
someone last week who
came into kind of eastern philosophy and
buddhism
from physics and it seems that there
seems to be a natural
gravity gravity there whether you're
studying
psychology in the mind or physics and
reality
there there always seems to be this
drift in those who study it deeply
towards
buddhism and eastern philosophy again
there's something just about the
understanding and right relationship of
what is
fully that that just seems to happen
quite naturally
and to have yeah to have to have you
articulate
some of those some of those concepts was
just beautiful and it's actually i think
one of the places we're going to start
here
we spoke earlier about the fact that
when i was thinking of what i wanted to
give people
with this it was mostly three things one
i wanted to give them something they
could walk
out with right after listening this
basically changed
or something they could put into
practice or at least
see differently the second was
some increased language a new vocabulary
that they can
orient themselves with and the third is
that i really want to
elucidate and dig into the religion
that's not a religion here
the stealing the culture and what what
moving forward with that actually looks
like in practice but
to give to give an example one of the
things this was a strange
this is actually something you speak
about in in the series where there are
some things that come
into your life that just jump out at you
they shine differently that
for me for me this was almost like an
alarm like it was like this is
this is extremely important dig into
this more and it was
one of your lectures on dukkha
the buddhist concept of dukkha and how
that
leads into uh what is known as
reciprocal narrowing
um that is that is i think
those two concepts um i think is one
thing we could give people
that would shift their life dramatically
right now
i don't know if you need much more of a
foundation than that but could we start
there
a talking about what that is and what
reciprocal
narrowing implies sure um what do you
want me to talk a bit about
the general background of dukkha and
then use that as a way of articulating
because i see reciprocal narrowing as a
component of
dukkha maybe if i gave that framework
that would be
helpful overall yeah it would be ideal
okay
great thank you uh so the buddhist
notion of dukkha is often translated as
suffering
and we tend to hear this incorrectly we
tend to hear this almost
as a synonym for pain
that's and that's similar to the way the
word mad now for us has become a synonym
for angry
whereas of course mad means insanity and
one of the things that can make you
insane
right it's anger right um yeah so in a
similar way we should see suffering
uh and and the way you can know this is
the case by the way it's by paying
attention
to the metaphors that the buddha uses to
describe
they're largely metaphors of
imprisonment
entrapment not being able to move a
forward stackedness and so you should
see suffering more as a loss of agency
rather than simply pain now pain can rob
you of agency
but many other things can rob you of
agency and so you have to really broaden
your
your notion of dukkha and what we want
to ask is what well what are the general
principles by which people lose
agency buddha the buddha said is no
matter where
you get you said like the ocean no
matter where you dip into it
you'll taste salt no matter where you
dip into his teaching you'll taste
freedom which is the restoration of
agency
so how do we lose agency well the idea
of dukkha is
uh i for me what what the buddha is
doing is he's articulating a kind of
perennial problem
that human beings fall prey to which is
the very machinery that makes us
intelligently adaptive makes us
perpetually susceptible to
self-deceptive self-destructive behavior
and as a cognitive scientist i study
this deeply and
and so i i'm deeply convinced of the
truth of this fundamental claim
that that's dukkha isn't sort of like an
external thing
like a devil that sort of sometimes
corrupts you it's that the very
machinery
that you depend upon for your agency is
also the same machinery
that can subject you to a loss of agency
through self-deceptive self-destructive
behavior
and so what happens in
dukkha it is
um that the adaptive machinery see
you have to understand that this
adaptive machinery works
in a a dynamical fashion it's not just
it's not like so when you're coming into
a scene your attention is
self-organizing
right you you're you can zoom into
details you can zoom out to the whole
picture
you can step back into your own mind you
can move forward to try and get to the
depths of my mind
and you're you're you're you're all
you're doing is tweaking that because
it's largely a very complex
self-organizing process
right now what that
means is the the the that
self-organizational nature
the way your cognition dynamically feeds
by itself
also means that you can get into what i
call uh parasitic processing
in which some some event happens to you
and then that self-organizing process
you people don't know
immediately what i'm talking about we
even have this language we talk about
things like
i get into an anxiety spiral right the
self-worth i start to ruminate or my
mind starts to race or i find that i'm
getting right
and so your mind this parasitic
processing
the the self-organizing
nature of your adaptive cognition
can also capture you like a parasite
and the fact that it's adaptive means
it's really hard for you to try and get
rid of it
because as you try and intervene and
stop
when you're ruminating well i shouldn't
be thinking that way that doesn't do
anything because it just reorganizes
yeah okay so if you have
that i'm going to try and put three
pieces together
so please be patient with me so you've
got this parasitic processing
the other thing people can do is they
can be
sort of deeply confused about
that dynamic relationship between them
and the environment
right so what do i mean by that this is
a notion from eric from
this is the notion that we um we have
existential modes i mean that's a
broader notion from existentialism
that means whenever i come into any
situation
and this is a part of that adaptive
machinery i was just talking about
right that self-organizing adaptive
machinery i
i in a dynamical fashion when i come
into any situation i assume
a particular identity and i assign a
bunch of identities so right now
i am the professor and you are
right the interviewer which of course
you're much more than that and i hope
i'm much more than just a professor
but i'm assuming an identity i'm
assigning an identity
and i'm doing that to sculpt the space
that i'm working in
is that okay does that make sense okay
now what from talked about is when we do
that that
process of co-identification we can do
it in
we can do it around different kinds of
needs we can order
we can organize that mode around the
having
needs these are needs that are met by
having things like having water having
oxygen having food
and what i want there is i want to i
want to assign i want to
assume the role of a manipulator and a
controller because i need to
control to manipulate water or i'm dead
and i need to assign categorical
identities oh that's water oh that's
also water
right and so things have their
categorical identity
so that i can easily manipulate them i
can easily replace them
i can't use that water all that water
over there will do right
and so the having mode is great it's
this control and manipulation
in terms of things categorical identity
uber calls it an
i it relationship and again there's
nothing wrong with that
but you also have needs that are met not
by having and controlling
these are net needs that are met by
becoming by developing
prime calls when they're your being
needs because they're met by you being a
certain way
like i need to be mature i need to be
wiser
i need to be in love and there
i'm not trying to control and manipulate
things and i'm trying to do something
else i'm trying to enter into right
relationship with things
right relationship and so
when i am with this woman who i'm deeply
in love with
i don't relate to her categorically in a
manipulative fashion
i don't say i'm with you because you
remind me of all other women and
therefore you're easily replaceable if i
need to replace you
and i can control and manipulate you and
consume you as i will
now that's a disaster and i'm never
going to be in love
to be in love means to not approach this
person
i yet but approach them i thought now
what we can do
is we can get modally confused we can
get morally confused in
what i mean by that we can try to
satisfy our being needs but within the
having modes
so instead of being mature we have a car
instead of being in love we have sex
right instead of being wise we have lots
of
nifty propositions we can assert
and that modal confusion will keep us
forever
spiritually hungry we will be frustrated
because we're not meeting the being
needs okay so let's say we're modelly
confused
and then within and notice how that's a
form
of parasitic processing it's adaptive
self-organization
that's coupling me to the world in a in
a way
that is deeply self-deceptive
self-destruction but i'm not aware of
so i'm caught up in this that leads me
to the third component
reciprocal narrowing
what's happening in reciprocal narrowing
is
right the parasitic processing and the
modal confusion
i'm assigning and assuming identities in
a way that the following thing is
occurring
and this is a notion taken from mark
lewis's ideas of what's happening in
addiction
so let's talk about addiction first
let's say i take the alcohol
the alcohol removes some of the
suffering and distress
right and so it's it's temporarily
alleviate
alleviating but it's actually it's very
it's a very self-deceptive thing to do
because it actually is impairing me
right and so
my cognitive flexibility goes down i
can't solve as many problems
and so the options for me in the world
goes down the world
narrows and then that's more threatening
to me right notice my freedom is going
away notice my freedom is going away
the world is threatening to me and oh no
so now i'm distressed so i rely on the
alcohol
a little bit more and i get narrowed a
little bit more
right and and that's alleviating because
i don't notice
oh but now the world is narrower and you
see what's happening
the world and my agency are reciprocally
narrowing until eventually
the world can be no other than it is and
i can be no other than
i am and that is addiction and that is
the complete
loss of freedom
so if you have right parasitic
processing
working within modal confusion that
brings about a reciprocal narrowing
that sucks away and robs all of your
life
that's dukkha and this is not because of
some strange or bizarre
influence it's because your cognition is
inherently self-organizing
the very processes that are making you
adaptively intelligent
are also subjecting you to
self-deception they are subjecting you
to
modal confusion and they are subjecting
you to reciprocal narrowing and you get
locked in to do good
but here's the point and i said this to
mark
in person because he's a friend of mine
good friend actually
good colleague if reciprocal narrowing
is possible
then so is reciprocal opening and if i
can be morally confused i can be morally
awake
i can wake up and remember how to be
in the bn mode as i reciprocally open
my identity and the identity of the
world and as i do
that i can become more and more aware
of my parasitic processing i can i can
interactive dynamical system that can
counteract
all of that machinery and reorient it
towards
a more like a more life enhancing way of
being
that's wisdom and that's the ecology of
practices i was talking about earlier
and so wisdom and a deeper connectedness
to oneself
and the world and each other it's
possible and
that wisdom could be comprehensive
enough that one was
reliably no longer totally confused
reliably capable of dealing with
parasitic processing
reliably capable of getting into a
flowing connection
with the world and other people
that would be enlightenment i would
argue at least that's one way of
understanding enlightenment
yeah yeah i've also actually recently i
just heard you use um
basically extended flow state also as a
as a label you could use for reciprocal
opening yes
yeah that is just it's so extremely
powerful
because for a few things there are a
number of ways that's extremely powerful
one is that it seems like in common
culture we most
people know the term downward spiral
if you said it to them and almost
everyone has
some sort of addict in their head when
they hear that
but if you then you know propose upward
spiral
that that term is very
very rarely spoken and it's like well
one implies the other
if it's possible to get stuck on a
roller coaster going down it's possible
to get stuck on one going up as well
very much and the thing is our culture
i mean i agree with arthur versus lewis
whose work i recommend
you know that the um the the cultural
grammar of spirituality in the west is
neoplatonism
and neoplatonism took had a term for
this which it took from plato which is
anagage
right and this is the ascent out of the
cave and this was a pervasive notion
within our wisdom tradition um
you know at the the journey of the mind
to god and saint bonaventure the neople
neoplatonic christianity had it as well
um
but with the loss of that tradition and
i am not
doing some sort of you know crypto
proselytizing for christianity here that
is not what i am doing
i'm going to say that again that's not
what i'm doing i'm also not trying to
dismiss christianity i i hope that
i'm dialogically in right relationship
with people who are
cultivating wisdom and enlightenment
christianity i want to throw no
obstacle in their way but i am not doing
that but what i'm saying is
when we lost that when we lost that
tradition that wisdom tradition
and those wisdom institutions we don't
carry around in our mind
the model of the monk the way as you
said we carry around the model of the
adam
and our culture doesn't give us that
acceptance
literature right so there you go
yeah yeah it's it's extremely important
again just having these frames
can shift can shift so much and it's
also why
you know i think a very unfair criticism
that's often
brought up for addicts is there's often
this offhand like oh yeah well why don't
they just do it differently
yeah and it's like it's not that simple
to your point it's not
static it's not this like bug in the
system it's
as much as you can work against it it
can work against you
and that becomes the hardest literally
like the hardest thing to do like
you see this in in some movies or
cartoons where the
the hero has to face the dark duplicate
of themselves
who is matched in all the skills it's
basically like that it's like
yeah strong as strong as you are it is
against you
and so it's not as simple as like yeah
well you should just snap your fingers
and again even even that frame i think
if we could take that culturally and
approach that to individuals with mental
illness or addiction or anything like
that
even that shifts the momentum in such a
way that
makes it extremely that's why i think
mark's work is so important
so i think mark's work is so important
the way he's reframing the notion of
addiction
not as a disease but as an embodied
embedded
inactive cycle of learning
that is i think really centrally
important i can't remember i can't
recommend his work enough
um i think that's really important i
mean mark has done so much good work
but if he's remembered for anything and
this happens at the culmination of his
career so that's good for him
um but um if he's remembered for
anything i hope
i hope people uh remember him for that
and that and
take note of that here's the thing i
want to say to you eric i mean so what
people like socrates and the buddha are
saying to us
is the difference between us and the
addict is only one of degree not a kind
we are also entrapped in multiple ways
and i'm including myself i have no
privileged position here we are also
entrapped in ways
uh that we are not aware of only we're
only indirectly aware of them
in how we suffer and this will allow me
to circle back that pervasive sense you
have
the in the meaning crisis the things
something is just not right and it's
gnawing away at everything
that's your indication that you're in
something deeply analogous
to like the the world the reciprocal
self-world narrowing
of the atoms yeah and then you know this
is why the first noble truth is
all life is suffering right it's like
you are constantly threatened
by this it it lurks it lurks in each
moment
waiting for the cascade to begin and i'm
glad
i'm glad yeah go ahead i just want to
say one thing
the comprehensiveness of this that you
put your finger on is really important i
just want to flag this for people
because there is a tendency in our
culture
to try to respond to this in a way that
seems
correct it seems and it seems even
spiritual to people
but it's deeply misleading right and
this is the idea that there is some
aspect of their psyche that is the safe
place
from dukkha oh wow but my gut
or my intuition no no my heart no no my
will
no no my my intellect no no my ex
and if you right any attempt to deify
any aspect of the psyche as the place
that is
the safe harbor from all of the tempest
of dukkha
is a fundamental mistake right it is
only
that's why the eightfold path is offered
or where you get all of the
the whole project around socrates and
the neoplatonic tradition
you have to that's why and this is to
give you
uh a a foreshadowing segue
that's why you need something as
comprehensive as a religion
uh to deal with this yeah yeah
that was a what would you call it that
was an underhand pitch
that was a setup right there and we we
are certainly building up to
uh to knock that out of the park um
but there there are some other
foundations i want to lay as we lead up
to this
because again i think we are going to
make the
i'm just going off camera for a sec
because i realize that my power is not
plugged in
good catch there we go this leads
quite leads quite nicely into the next
the next um
kind of term i wanted to bring up for
people because it seems like
dukkha is one of these which is you use
the term perennial problems
that humans face a lot and i noticed
this
in my own life where you know sometimes
my friends and i will talk
and you know it's just like well and
we'll give an answer to a problem that
someone's facing and it's like well
why are we just discovering this now you
know why did it take me
into my late 20s to figure this out and
it's like well it
shouldn't have people wrote this down a
long time ago
we've just lost the we've just lost the
practices we've lost the ideas we've
lost the scripture that actually
afforded those answers much earlier but
so can we give a
can we give an overview of um and i
would argue maybe
maybe you would say something
differently that that dukkha and
reciprocal narrowing
are one of the perennial problems faced
by
humanity are there any uh can you list
some others or just
yeah and i think you're the notion of
the scriptures i mean one way
of um re-capturing
i mean and jordan peterson brought uh i
mean i have like
i have i have a very complex relation
with jordan peterson
he's a colleague and a friendly
colleague and he supports my work
and i think there's a lot of insight in
him but i also have criticisms of his
work
but i do think one of the things he did
that was of great value was to reawaken
people
via jung you should have also done
corban as well but
bayern young to the importance of myth
because i think one of the things that
myth does
for us is it gives us a dramatic and for
reasons we'll talk about later
we need a dramatic and not a merely
propositional
presentation of these perennial problems
um
and so for example for every good hero
myth
which you know is the perennial problem
of you know self-transcendence
and going through uh having to face very
serious
frame breaking and loss in order to
afford that kind of growth
there's also a counterbalancing myth of
hubris and
what weight remember that you're mortal
you'll never be a god
and that doesn't mean that you you won't
you'll keep progressing towards it no
you'll always be in your very bones
immortal
you'll always be threatened by dukkha
etc so i think myth is an important
thing
uh to remember so
if you look at myth and you look at your
sacred scriptures you can see a lot of
perennial problems
uh that come up a lot
and so let's take let's take a myth that
and people won't even recognize it as a
myth but it is and it's myth in the
sense i'm using it shakespeare's hamlet
like why why do people keep reading
about this danish guy
right from from like you know the 17th
century like who
who cares well because this is a
perennial problem
human beings are beset with their
they're gifted by
and beset by being self-conscious
and that means we right if you look at
hamlet
he towers above the people around him
and shakespeare is using him
as an exemplar of this human capacity
for
we can rise above our impulses unlike
many other animals
we are not merely what frankfurt calls
wantons
we don't just like because i just give
in to every impulse my impulses are
contradictory
right they are they're they undermine
each other right i want it i want to
look good and be sexually attractive but
i want the chocolate cake and oh
right and all that sort of impulsivity
right
and so we can and this is bellman's
point
i can i have this capacity of a
you know and it's the capacity that
mindfulness trains right i can step back
and look at my own perspective
and we'll talk about later why that
require notice how that's already
another kind of knowing
perspectival knowing and we'll come into
that i hope but i can step back and look
at my perspective
and you could say well i
this has to do with the logistics of the
psyche i won't
give much of my resources and my energy
to this impulse right now
and i'll try and redirect towards this
impulse and we can do all that
and and you know thank god we can
because
we would be sort of monstrous if we
could but the problem with that with
that
self-consciousness that ability to step
back and reflect
is it disconnects us uh from that
machinery
because like when i'm thirsty and i'm
seriously kind of
impulsively i don't i'm not aware of my
thirst
i'm aware through my thirst of
everything right
things i'm seeing the world thirstily
but when i step back and look at my
thirst
the perspective from which i'm looking
at my thirst is not one of thirst
it's perhaps one of curiosity or perhaps
one of frustration
right but it's a different motivation
and so i'm now actually disconnected
from the motivational energy of thirst
i'm no longer seeking for water
but you know what i can do with that
curiosity i can step back and look at
that
and now i'm no longer curious about my
thirst right and i can
right and so i i can get caught up
right in this perspective that
completely disconnects me
from my motivational machinery so
this and this is hamlet's tragedy
right he keeps thinking and reflecting
and reflecting on his reflecting and
acting about
and people are dying around him and
going insane around him and
there's this tragedy building around him
right and so our self-consciousness
and there's a perennial problem of
how do we deal with that and you know
and that interacts with other like i
mentioned it
you know we are self we are subconscious
of our death
in our mortality in a way that other
animals aren't
how do we deal with that there's
perennial problems around absurdity my
ability to self transcend
means i can
rise above myself to i get to this
cosmic perspective and now it seems like
from that cosmic perspective all of the
minutia of my own motivation and
concerns seems so insignificant
so trivial life seems absurd
and this of course is something
developed very well
um in the work of camus i'm reading the
plague right now because of covet
and reacquainting with camus so we face
perennial problems of absurdity we face
perennial problems of
the reflectiveness gap caused by our
self-consciousness
we reflect because we are perspectival
we we face perennial problems of
egocentrism
and narcissism because we face perennial
problems
like you said around dukkha around
self-deceptive self-destructive behavior
modal confusion reciprocal narrowing we
face perennial problems
uh of
of how do i want to say it
there's a family of problems loneliness
or culture
shock or future shock in which we feel
like
even again in hamlet like the time is
out of joint we feel
in the in the bones of our psyche we
feel that we don't belong we don't fit
in
we're not we're not at one we with the
environment
we feel homeless and that's a perennial
problem a sense of
sort of spiritual dominance this is not
an exhaustive list but does this give
you a good sense of what i'm talking
about
yeah absolutely yeah that was how myth
is a place to look like hamlet for where
these parental problems
are being played out yeah well i think
uh
the way the way it's come up for me is
uh due to your human nature due to the
fact that you are a self-aware human
there's a host and when when you just
went off on that list
to me it was like a hydra it was just
like holy shit like i can address one
and three others come up and
yes yes it was uh it seems fundamentally
um that the
the problems con concern your right
relationship
to yourself to others into the world
exactly exactly
exactly right and again we get to this
is why it loops back to myth and this is
why i think jordan peterson has grown a
little bit which is
that is for the most part outside of the
domain of science
it doesn't matter that i know you exist
that tells me nothing about how i should
relate to you
and whether i should feel threatened
should i feel happy like all that
and when that's taken when that
confusion of how to relate to something
applies to
yourself other people and everything
around you
you end up in no man's land
you end up in just this void of
what the fuck is going on like and
it creates this that's why i think you
get
things like the rise in mental health
crisis you get the rise in nihilism you
just get this
what on earth and i think to the crux of
some of your work is
when these perennial problems reach a
critical mass
because we're we've lost the the ways of
knowing
the actual practices that address them
we end up in something like the meaning
crisis
yes exactly that was beautifully said
you should have done some of my series
that was really well
um i mean what you just said eric is
exactly the case that
for for historical reasons
and and forces that are still at work uh
we have
we have lost um the practices the
ecology of practices the communities
um um for wisdom because that's the name
i would give to that
that knowing how and knowing through a
transformation how to get into right
relationship
with yourself with each other in the
world we've lost that
in a profound way um
and
means that we we don't even have a
a like well like you said we don't know
where we are
we don't have a world view that
homes that pursuit of wisdom and
legitimates it and valorizes it
and and justifies it to us and uh
inspires us to aspire to it we don't
have a worldview that does any of that
for us
so when we are beset by the perennial
problems and we turn for wisdom
we have nowhere to turn so when the
perennial problems
are basically unleashed because we have
no homing world view
that homes an ecology of practices that
will allow us to deal with that monster
then that is the meeting crisis yeah
yeah and as as almost
responses or actually i would say
something like tools in your tool belt
that you can use
i think two things come up one is the
four ways of knowing
right and one and the other is psycho
technologies
can we touch on both of those yeah um so
part of the historical forgetting that
has cut us off from wisdom
is a is a is a historical
process in which our cultural cognitive
grammar
what i mean by that by a cultural
cognitive grammar are sort of the
fundamental patterns by of
intelligibility the fundamental sort of
the fundamental and uh both individually
and culturally habitual ways in which we
formulate
our problems and think about things and
conceive of them
and try to remember that conceive
originally meant to give birth
um so um
one of the fundamental forgettings that
has happened
is we have forgotten the kinds of
knowing
that make sense of which of this notion
of wisdom
so the kind of knowing that
we have reduced knowing to what i call
propositional knowing
and this is the kind of knowing that is
our grasping of facts
um that we assert in propositions that
we believe
like i know that cats are mammals there
we go
there's a fact and i'm asserting a
belief
and then of course we've developed and
and i'm a scientist so i think this is a
very very good thing by the way
we have developed uh of dealing
with how self-deception creeps into the
inferential processes
by which we manipulate propositions and
generate good
theory good belief that's what the
scientific and historical methods are
and i have training in both mostly in
science but in some history as well
right and so and so i believe
in science in that sense i think that
science is a great way
of knowing propositionally but as you
alluded to earlier the problem with that
is that inferential propositional
knowing is not it's not
identical with all of our ways of
knowing
and it's what's really significant is
that propositional knowing
and we know this theoretically there's a
little bit of irony there we know this
because of the ongoing science of
meaning in life
we know that those kinds of beliefs do
very very little to make your life
meaningful
right precisely because they don't
empower you to deal with
these perennial problems and they don't
empower you well with
you know deepening the connections to
yourself to each other in the world
so let's go through the other kinds of
knowing that actually have to do with
that
so propositions are good when they're
true and that's great but notice what we
didn't have
power all the power well but power
matters
because you have another kind of knowing
that isn't that doesn't come to
fruition in truth it comes its sense of
realness is
power and this is knowing how this is
your procedural knowing this is knowing
how to do things knowing how to row a
boat knowing how to walk
knowing how to talk right above and
beyond any proposition you utter
you need to know how to talk it empowers
you
and if you didn't if you didn't have the
power of speech think about how
disconnected from reality you would
become in so many ways
so right this is your procedural knowing
this is and it doesn't result in
theories it results in skills
when you know when you have good
know-how you have
powerful skills and that's expertise
right
and part more meaningful people for
people
is if they have some sense of that kind
of
fulfillment of procedural knowing in
having some kind of power
that they can they have reliable skills
for interacting
with themselves with each other and with
the world
and some of those reliable skills have
to specifically be
skills of dealing with perennial
problems
okay well whenever i'm am i using all my
skills right now
i'm a tai chi player right i i i have so
much
but i'm not using my tai chi skills
right now well maybe
in some generalized sense but many of my
skills that i don't i'm not bringing to
bear
well how do i know which skills to apply
and which skills to acquire well that's
well that's based on your situational
awareness well what kind of knowing is
that well that's your perspectival
knowing
that's knowing that that's your salience
landscaping that's how
that's how things that you're knowing
through your particular state of
consciousness
this is the difference between knowing
your room when you're drunk and knowing
your room when you're sober
or knowing your room when you're happy
and knowing your room when you're sad
right it's what stands out for you
what's salient what's foregrounded
what's background
it's your sense of here now here now
here known as connectedness and so that
doesn't come to fulfillment
in a sense of truth or a sense of power
it comes into fulfillment in a sense of
presence that's what we're trying to get
in video games
we're trying to get that sense of
presence because that means
right my my my perspectival knowing
i i'm i have i've got i've got
situational awareness
that is allowing me to apply and acquire
the skills i need
so you see how the propositional knowing
depends on the procedural knowing
all the propositions depend on me
knowing how to speak
right but knowing how to speak and how
to apply my other skills
depends on my perspectival knowing my
situational awareness
but what does that depend on well that
depends on
my participatory knowing that depends on
the fact
that i'm ultimately coupled to the world
in the right way
that that i that agent arena
relationship
that i was talking about earlier in
reciprocal narrowing and opening
that it is taking place that's not
something i can make
think about it all right think about um
loneliness
when you're lonely well what i just i'm
just i'm not going to be lonely now like
you can kind of sort of
but what's what's what's wrong there is
that there isn't a proper
like mutual fittedness between you and
the world
because you need another person so
participatory knowing is well think
about this
it's about how your biology this is
called niche construction in biology
how your biological evolution has
co-shaped your environment
and you so that there are these
relationships of belonging they're
called affordances
in kansai and gibson um so but
right um like you have a category i
assume
food right so there's an apple and
it affords nourishment to you you see it
as
food right because evolution has shaped
you
and that environment you you right you
have niche construction
and you can grasp the apple and eat it
and so it's food for you does it is that
okay
yeah also notice notice how culture has
shaped you
and your environment you're in a nice
room and you're speaking english
did you make english did you make the
room you're in
no how about the technology you're using
none of it okay so your biology shapes
you to the world and the world to you
your culture shapes you to the world
and you and and and write you the world
to you
and now your brain your embodied brain
in that dynamical coupling
right it's shaping the world and you to
the world
it's creating a particular configuring
of agency
and it's calling out particular things
as relevant and important to you
right this is what bickenstein meant
when he said that even if lions could
talk i wouldn't i couldn't understand
them
because they have a different biology
they don't have culture
they don't have language but right right
so that's participatory knowing
the participatory knowing makes all the
niches
makes all the affordances and then
the perspectival knowing turns those
affordances into a situation of which
you are aware
that situational awareness trains and
affords you applying skills in your
procedural knowing
so you are empowered and then finally in
your empowerment
you can utter particular propositions
and undertake to justify and defend them
in your propositional knowing
but if you if you think that all of that
what you are and all that you know
is your propositional knowing and that
all i have to do to
transform you is change your belief
which is the fundamental liability of
ideology
right and you are not only being lied to
you are being cut off
from all of this machinery and think
about how that perspective procedural
empowerment
that perspectival presence and that
participatory belonging
think about how belonging presence and
power are
so central to your sense of meaningful
existence
and if you're cut off from them you're
cut off from the wisdom
that affords that kind of meaning
yeah and the wow hey there was a lot
there
again this is why this is why i want i
want this
grammar introduce the world because it
orients you in such a beautiful way um
a we see this come up in a lot there are
a lot of i feel like common cliches
that address this at some level you know
the classic one like talk is cheap
like dude i like all the armchair sports
commentators
oh i could do that i could do that
simply because i know that he needs to
dribble the ball and go up and dunk it
that in no way means you you know it
deeply enough to actually do it
that's right it's a that's a huge
disconnect
there's also um it's the same reason why
you know you should eat healthy and
don't
right knowledge is in no way enough for
that
um and then
it it feels to me in a way and i may be
incorrect on this but it feels like
essentially the resurgence of perennial
problems
the growing force of the meaning crisis
is almost a natural result of the fact
that you could say western material
science
is so propositional it's
almost solely abstract right and all
these four ways of knowing are almost on
a spectrum
of conceptual to fully embodied
right and if you if your whole culture
if your whole
understanding and approach to the world
is entirely theoretical
you're lost in a world of abstraction
and you're disconnected from the
here and now and that's why even in in
movies right when the the main character
is going off
what it takes is being slapped in the
face right it's like right here
like get back here and something i
wanted to ask you about this
because hey i don't even know if that
that spectrum is fair
but it definitely feels that way that it
goes from conceptual to
deeply embodied and it feels absolutely
fair i think that's absolutely fair
beautiful and yes they are they are all
essential i'm not going to discount any
of them
but what i want to bring up is it seems
like it seems like eastern culture and
western culture
have picked to set up camp at
the opposing polls it seems like western
culture is up in the
propositional procedural
and eastern philosophy has chosen to set
up camp almost
solely at perspectival and participatory
the example coming up for me very
directly is zen
zen is almost mercilessly in the here
and now
like just stop conceptualizing stop
abstracting right here right now you
know the wind is blowing through the
trees
and that is all you need to know
is that fair does that land i think
that's fair i mean insofar
as i mean i i think that's
a prototypical representation of eastern
philosophy
i do not know how much asiatic and
south asiatic cultures are now oriented
that way because of globalization
what you just said um our the culture's
emphasis on
propositional knowing and a kind of a
kind of procedural knowing technological
going
has greatly of course empowered the west
whatever the west is
um and to do
i mean a worldwide kind of imperialism
and so whether or not that's actually
the case because
what and i'm not trying to say this
because i'm not trying to make a
political point here
um or at least that's not my total
intent my intent is
that i think versions of the meeting
crisis are now
uh are are now becoming important in
japan
china um etc um
so um i i i doubt
that any sort of comprehensive journey
to the east for example like
i'm not accusing you of being overly
romantic i'm just i'm just saying that
um i think the meeting crisis is now
becoming a global issue
that being said so that's an important
caveat i think your central insight is
exactly correct
so i was not trying to put it aside i
was trying to just situate it
within a proper context of understanding
i think the
uh for historical reasons uh that have
to go back
to changing the way we read and the rise
of nominalism and a whole bunch of stuff
i talk about
towards belief and ideology and
assertion
um and that the only all that really
mattered was the competition
uh you know the political competition
between ideologies
and and and and the
sort of the political competition
between ideologies
to see who got most access to the power
that science and technology was putting
in our hands
and so i think yeah the west has gotten
oriented that way
these eastern philosophies do put a
tremendous
emphasis on as you said
transformation of the perspective of the
participatory
reciprocal narrowing is a strangling of
participatory knowing
so that perspectival knowing loses all
of its capacity for insight
right so trying to
you're trying to give people that
non-ideological transformative
capacity to perspective and
participatory knowing was definitely
emphasized the price that was paid for
that emphasis of course
was that the
the potential opening of the world
that is provided by the scientific
framework was also not afforded
um so i you know i i love zen
uh i i know people who practice it and
in some ways on prototypicals that
because in my life i integrate a taoist
tai chi with a
with a you know teravated pasta which is
sort of proto at least proto-chan
right um but i also don't
want to give up the way
uh you know what science has supported
us because
look at what just happened and look look
who the people were
yeah the people who and i did it i
taught meditation
i continued to do during coven and
giving peace
transformative ability right to deal
with
you know the perennial problems that are
being exacerbated by the covid
crisis and the way it's making the
meaning crisis like
definitely but who was also out there
really making
a huge difference it's the scientists
yeah they're the people who are actually
giving us
the tools that we need to deal with
covet so
again uh you weren't saying this and i'm
not attributing it to it but i
you know a kind of crypto orientalism in
which the east is
you know you know is is bright and pure
and we are just you know a horrible the
horrible way
i think that is we should give up we
should give that up that's
that's analogous to trying to find the
one part of you that is free from dukkha
right we need to we what we need and so
sorry
i'm trying to make a really central
point for me and i don't need to be
going on
we need something that properly
and deeply integrates science and
spirituality together
that's why i'm making this little speech
right now yeah
yeah and it's definitely worth that that
level of underscore because it
is far too common um
far too common in some spaces right now
and uh
yeah the the the easiest offhand like
mantra that's come up for me is
and this is by no means my creation um
both and right if you're ever in a
situation
where you're viewing something as either
or it's definitely not it's probably
both and
like you need you need the compliments
of both uh and
science and spirituality is arguably one
of the most
powerful instances of that
thank you for saying that because i
think the challenge facing us
this is the way of sort of sharpening
the issue of the meeting crisis
we've said like together
and i appreciate your help on this you
said you know
historical forces have uh
have disarmed us in our ability to
respond to perennial problems
but any attempt to address the meeting
crisis
has to do what we were also just talking
about i would argue it has to
reintegrate science and spirituality
together in order to give us
what we need to respond to the meeting
crisis no our deepest
all of our knowings have to be put into
right relationship with each other
yeah yeah and like look like it's also
it's also just
historically true that early
christianity
was responsible for the dissemination
and exploration of a lot of science
right there's a this is again another
kind of trope that
misses the mark a little bit which is
you know science is the process of
cutting things up
and kind of deadens the world and makes
it all not as beautiful
but actually it's not true at all like
it makes it more beautiful the deeper
you this is what sports is a good
example i guess
like it's great to watch professional
athletes do their thing
it's even better to have tried it
yourself to see how difficult and how
nuanced it is and to know
what moves they're actually doing and
then to watch them do it with that level
of grace
it actually improves it and it's like
well
that applies to all of this happening
here as well
right like it doesn't get more beautiful
knowing just how nuanced
atoms and molecules and nonsense and
quantum physics is it actually is
more amazing it enchants the world
rather than
uh i think thank you for saying that i
mean
the scientific worldview doesn't give us
like
the what we need for wisdom but it also
doesn't do it like
like what you said i i would i would
strengthen it
and perhaps be a little bit more
aggressive than you would which is huge
unusual because i'm usually
not in that position i would say
it's a bit it's unfair
here let me use an analogy i think it
would be unfair to
criticize a particular religion if you
and i think many people do criticize it
unfairly if you didn't make some
real good faith effort no pun intended
to experience it from the inside
like the way an anthropologist goes and
does participant notice the word
participant observation notice
participant
observation perspective or participatory
knowing right of another culture if you
don't do deep participant observation of
a religion
you don't really and don't get some
sense i'm not saying be converted
don't get some sense of what it is from
the inside and just criticizing it from
the outside is really unfair because you
missed it
it's like it's like you you know when
you you criticize
a couple's relationship you don't know
what it's like from the inside for them
right in a typical in a sorry in it not
a typical in an in an analogous way
people who criticize science and haven't
practiced it
at least done some significant good
faith participant observation in it
and make all these pronouncements about
unfair it's just fundamentally unfair
i i practice science and i you've heard
me in our discussion
criticize its deep inadequacies but
simply
demonizing it i agree with you i think
that is a fundamental mistake
and so we need to we need to put
science and spirituality into deep
conversation but that goes that goes
both ways you just said it
you know we need to acknowledge how much
of the scientific world
is dependent not only the scientific
world the secular world
is dependent on christianity paul vander
clay has done just a whole bunch of
video work you know building on the work
of many other people tom hall and others
trying to show you know how much
of what we consider secular and
scientific was given birth conceived
by christianity and so um
we need to you know again a
foreshadowing
we need to have a deep dialogue
between uh science and spirituality
yeah yeah and so uh
actually one point that came up was it's
almost hard to judge something
unless you participate in the practices
that came from it
uh i think this is like a lot of people
criticize christianity but have you ever
tried like
real prayer like actually seeing what
that does to your body and how you
and how you feel and perhaps even how it
ripples into your life
same thing with uh you know meditation
practice going to halls of worship like
unless you've done the practices that
stem from these ideas
like yeah the ground to criticize it is
very weak and very frail
yeah and and it it reverberates
backwards too
like i think
like i i didn't really get
until i had been practicing tai chi for
a very long time
yeah perfect example perfect example of
it
um i'm actually going to float this to
you
there are two ways we can go right now
um one is
i i want to dig into the meat right both
steal the culture and the religion
that's not a religion
do you feel that it's necessary to load
in psychotex
and the ecology of practices before we
do that
well i mean i could do a very quick riff
because we i've alluded to it
many times on the ecology practices and
psychotech doesn't won't take me that
long
to try that okay so the ecology of
practices
um you've heard me so let's go back and
maybe do a bit of a narrative biography
because that gives people an access
point
i was taught in ecology of practices um
and so i was taught i was taught a
meditative practice
and in meditation it's a mindfulness
practice in which you're stepping back
and looking at your framing
um i often use the example of like my
glasses my glasses
the way my glasses frame my vision i
look through them in the sense of
by means of them and beyond them uh
right i also have a mental framing that
i'm always looking through
and by means of and what i can do when
my glasses are dirty is i can step back
and look at them to see if there's any
gunk on them that's what you're doing in
meditation you're stepping back and
looking at
the mental framing but if all i ever did
think about it if all i ever did was
step back and look at my glasses
look at the gunk whoa look whoa well
how do i know if i actually have
corrected my glasses
i have to put them on and then look out
and see if i can see more deeply and
more
clearly into the world that's
contemplation right
that contemplation that the word the
center of it is temple
to look out to look into the heavens
originally that's what i meant
or uh it's it's contemplation is the
latin word for the greek word peoria
which means to look deeply into things
not theory by the way
that the word theory is a derivative
from this more perspectival ability
right so notice how those are in a
complementary relationship
one gets me to step back and look at so
that i can see distortion
one gets me to right to step through and
look beyond
and that allows me to learn and to see
what i couldn't see before and i need
both for transformation
notice that we put these together
without thinking of it in a word that
we've inherited from eckhart
breakthrough
i have to break the bad framing through
into something beyond right breakthrough
and so notice what i'm trying to get in
is that
practices have respective strengths and
weaknesses
and they need to be put into a
complementary relationship
the problem with those two practices for
example is they're
they're both very heavy practices
they're taking place in your head as
you're still
so you know what you need to complement
them with a moving practice
a mindfulness practice like tai chi
chuan that also
teaches you more about the flow state
and see
that practice though if i'm just moving
it's hard for me to develop mindfulness
and
you see what i'm trying to show you they
have they have sets of strengths and
weaknesses
and what you want to do is like an
ecology you want to put them into a
dynamical system
where they're constraining informing and
right
affording each other in powerful ways
and
you also need practices that
bridge you right between different kinds
of knowing
so i teach lectio divina which is a way
of reading
sacred reading that helps you to bridge
between
the propositional and the perspectival
and the participatory
or chanting which helps to bridge from
the participatory
right and the perspective into the
propositional right so you want you also
want bridging practices
you also layer practices on top of each
other
so mata looking out
and the pasta looking in can be layered
on to each other the way my left and
right
visual fields can be layered onto each
other so i can see into depth
and when i layer them onto each other i
like
what can emerge as prajna this non-dual
awareness that is simultaneously deeply
out and deeply in
so what i'm trying to do is i'm trying
to put practices together into a
complement
relationships of complementarity
relationships that link between the
kinds of knowing
and relationships that layer the
practices developmentally onto each
other
so i have this self-correcting
self-transforming
ecology of practices that's an ecology
of practices
is that okay yeah and and just a quick
bookmark you'll notice how the end
description of that sounded exactly like
dukkha and reciprocal narrowing
but in a good way right that's also
that's also a foreshadow there
um yeah that was perfect and then i
think if we can get
uh psycho technologies so
the idea is and this is uh this is i
think
andy clark has said this profoundly
angry park is an example of
a really important cognitive scientist
and somebody who's associated with what
it's called 4e cognitive science
um i i really respect his work i have
criticisms of it as a scientist
but um i recommend people reading his
work but he has a book called natural
born cyborgs
that because we're inherently cultural
beings
we have evolved across species to
fit the world to us and us to the world
remember i was talking about that that
mutual fitness participatory night well
what's an example of fitting the world
to
us and us to the world tools tools
like my phone like my watch like this
mug like this glass
it fits my hand right so that the world
can better fit my hand
water i can carry around the liquid so
we have evolved our brains have evolved
to merge with tools that's what a cyborg
is
right now those the examples i gave were
physical tools
they are designed to fit our body
and extend it into the world and also
extend the world into the body to fit
the world and
the body better together but there are
also psycho technologies that are
designed to fit the way our minds work
so that right we can extend our mind
into the world and also extend the world
into the mind
a classic example of this is literacy
so a psychotechnology isn't a skill
because it is
socially creative if you didn't make
literacy i didn't make literacy
right it is a socially standardized this
is the importance of distributed
cognition but most of our thinking is
done
in concert with other people right
so literacy is a socially standardized
way
of formatting information processing
the manipulation storage and
transmission of information
such that it fits my cognition well and
compensates for it empowers it
so with literacy i can now store
information outside of my own memory
i can reflect on my own cognition
outside of my own consciousness
i can link my mind to yours i can link
my current mind to my future mind by
writing things down
i can massively empower myself so a
psychotechnology is a socially generated
standardized way of formatting
communicating transmitting information
that is the socially designed
to fit cognition well fit it generally
so that it's widely disseminable about
amongst the population
unlike these particular skills for
example and afford
a comprehensive and reliable empowerment
cognition
in some way literacy is an example
numeracy is an example
graphing is an example mindfulness is an
example by the way
yeah so those are sacral technologies
yeah
mindfulness and graph paper were the
ones that just
flipped the entire switch for me it was
like oh this had to be invented
like we actually created this it didn't
just get pulled from the ether
and that's right yeah so let's
i think we have built a very good
foundation let's see where our
arc has taken us right so we have
as a human you have perennial problems
that basically lurk under the surface
like some beast in the ocean always
threatening you
i really like the analogy of the hydra
because as you address one
it it reorients new ones come up
and when enough heads arise you get
something like the meeting crisis
the meeting crisis left unattended can
basically
serve an existential threat for a tribe
or for
humanity at large right it could be
people just offing themselves it could
be war
it could be anything right not good not
good to let continue over time
so people recognize this and they're
like okay we need to do something about
this
um from that right we had the ecology of
practices that grew
and different communities would would
develop different ecologies and
practices
they developed different psychotechs all
all done to help
would you would you call it make an
agreement between the four ways of
knowing
and how they show up in relationships to
themselves to others and the world
and through that and to your point about
the ecology
it was dynamic and self-organizing
enough and it had a feedback loop
that as the threats dynamically
reorganized it could
dynamically reorganize in response to
that
the first thing i want to say is notice
how absolutely
necessary that is for you as an
individual and
any community at large like that's
non-negotiable
if you want to stay alive and stay sane
while you're alive
so it's absolutely necessary and so what
happens
when a group of people who have
recognized the need for this are trying
to carry it out
come together you know a some people
give some good answers
some people share some good ideas and
then some people are like hey that's
really good idea you should write that
down
or like do you want to meet next week to
talk about this
and you can see already that you have
the basis of something that looks like
religion
you have an organized community carrying
out a set of practices that help put
them in
relationship with themselves others in
the world awesome
right so and i i think i think we've
both
we've both tipped a hat to i think this
is something that jordan peterson has
brought up to the surface quite well
that there is that there is a need there
is a
individual psychological and a
collective
institutional need for something like a
religion
it might not have to be any of the
current instantiations of it
but you really don't want to go without
it
because you can argue we live in a
global world that is largely without it
right now
right we've moved the nuns the the
people who have
no real religion are a i think the
largest group
and b the largest growing group
and we are smack dab in the middle of a
meeting crisis
almost all of our crises jordan halls
calls us the meta crisis right
we just have a crisis of crises and
we're bouncing around through it and so
it's like we now
we have a very visceral example of what
happens when we move away from that
so it's like okay that that experiment's
probably not great
one thing i would would like to
speak to a little bit here is so if we
do have
a need for something that looks like a
religion
um and actually maybe i'll bookmark this
as separate from just an individual
spiritual practice
because you just you know you can learn
you can learn from your elders way
faster than you can make all the
mistakes yourself
so there there's a there's a place for
religion why
then are we looking to reinvent a new
one
rather than what is wrong with the ones
already
in existence that have sustained for
several thousand years
like why not why not religion 1.0 why
why now is there a almost an inadequacy
in them
yeah that's really good so that that's
that's
that should be the culminating question
because that's going to take a lot
um so
i mean i've been exploring with my my
dear friend and colleague who i should
have mentioned earlier
uh christopher masterpiece he's very
much my partner
and a lot of this i owe a lot of this to
chris
uh the work we do together um and also
the work
that i've done with theo ferraro on
wisdom so i just want to
make sure that people are aware of that
but chris and i are
exploring uh with andrew sweeney um a
notion i got
from kerry in his book on augustine
um this latin term inventio
is becoming central to me sorry i'm on
the edge of sneezing that's why i got
this off look at my face
he wrote this book and he was trying to
talk about how
uh augustine afforded sort of the the
current sense we have of an inner self
um and augustine basically takes sort of
platinus
and does this really interesting thing
with his own
personal sense of autobiography he makes
the autobiographical inner self
which we all now take to be natural but
once again
it's a historical phenomena but that's
the point i want to make
because we're inherently cultural
biological beings we need a term that
that sits on on both of those so the
word inventio
means both to make
and to discover it's both something
you're making
and so the word invention is you just
make it and the word is discovery you
just find it but inventio is
you're making it but you're also
discovering it
uh and so in a sense what i'm
trying to do is to re the reinventio of
religion so that sense of connectedness
that we've been talking about
throughout connectedness to yourself to
each other to the world in depth
i actually use a word religio to talk
about that
that is one of the one of i think it's
the preferred
potential etymological origins for the
word religion itself
the sense of binding and connectedness
so i think
and and this has been deeply influenced
by the work of james carson others
i think that the the function of
religions and
so i got to do this careful i i argue
that the function of religion is to give
us an ecology of practices
and wealth and well-vetted psychotech
that will address the perennial problems
and enhance religion
yeah but notice that
no religion actually says it that way
[Laughter]
um and
instead and again i've been careful to
note that i don't use this word
pejoratively
religions have what i would call a
mythological way
of trying to activate that functionality
right yeah and that mythos
has it depends like all mythos
on a world view that properly
situates it and connects it to
a wisdom tradition is that okay yeah
perfect
this a set of revolutions
right in the past that i mean cultural
cognitive cognitive revolutions not so
much political revolutions
you know like the renaissance the
reformation the scientific revolution
have sundered that mythos that we
inherited from the axial age
the mythos of the two worlds and this
world being less real
and the way that got solidified
and i would even argue ossified in the
west into
this this categorical difference between
the natural and the supernatural
uh and between and a categorical a
disconnect between them
and a categorical disconnection between
faith and spirituality and reason and
science that's something that are
deeply opposed to each other because one
is the doorway to the supernatural the
other is the doorway to the natural
whether or not this is actually how all
christians practice or believe
i think that's a very open question i
meet many christians
paul vander clay jp marceau harry cohen
uh jonathan pedro that are in some
significant way trying to
i think reformulate that grammar um
in a powerful way but regardless
that history of that mythos
and its disconnect from the scientific
worldview
because it's written into the grammar of
that mythology is its disconnect and its
opposition
and the way science has developed a
counteractive mythos
right that's antagonistic towards
religion
you know it politically tolerates it
because that's polite but it's
ultimately antagonistic
right and so we've got this
profoundly grotesquely stupid
separation sorry i don't usually let
this strong but this is the part that
really bothers me
between knowledge right and wisdom
which is like the ancient greeks would
go what what is going on there
right i think that
the existing religions are so bound up
and especially christianity but i think
this
buddhism especially western buddhism
because it has a two world mythos
and there are definitely versions of zen
i encounter them that are
anti-scientific anti-intellectual
in a profound way as if that again is
the way to liberation right
i don't think the existing religions
have the capacity to bridge between
science and spirituality in a w
within a pluralistic dynamically
complexifying world
in a way that isn't needed right now to
address the meeting crisis
they were crafted in a different time
within a different history
within a different mythos like
christianity did not grow up in
pluralism it did not grow up
right in in a in a scientific world view
that is massively successful
right i can go on and on and i do in
this series
what i'm trying to say is that
the religions that we have and i have
done participatory observation
in at least three of them deeply
christianity buddhism taoism
and i they are like my family i owe
much to them and i am respectful and i
have a loving
attitude towards them or even
neoplatonism uh within the west same
thing
deeply family deeply in love with it but
ultimately none of those
are have the framework that is needed
for bringing about the deep
integration between science and
spirituality within a pluralistic
massively dynamically complexifying
world and this is jordan hall's point
right we are facing not only complexity
but
a accelerating complexification of
complexity
right i don't think the existing
religions
have what it takes and i say that with
love
and respect for them and i recommend
that people
and i have tried to reinvent you as much
instead of salvage which i used to use
which
sounds like they're broken in some ways
but i try to reinvent you from the
existing religions
not just me myself but other all these
people all these communities and
practices like rave kelly and
all these other people that i'm meeting
right and you've alluded to all these
communities that are
taking shape all around the world
i think that
that we can reinvent you
a new ecology of practices new
psychotech
and new myth with us
that's a more of an artistic project
that will reintegrate science and
spirituality within within a pluralistic
complex dynamically complexifying world
such that we can now address the meeting
process that's what i'm holding up
now here's what i want to say and i say
this and i say there's a dialogue
with people of of the existing faiths
that is not a foreclosure argument
it's not a deductive argument that's a
that's where i'm placing my bat's kind
of argument
it's almost like a pascalian wager with
all due respect to pascal
right it's possible that christianity or
buddhism
because they've done it before could
reorganize themselves like you know
buddhism integrated with taoism to
become chair
right and then it integrated with shinko
to become zen right
and you know neoplatonism and
christianity were able to integrate
and it was able to integrate
aristotelian science maybe christianity
or maybe buddhism or maybe some
right religion may be able to
reformulate itself in such a way
that it can do what i'm proposing but i
just don't see it happening
collectively i see it happening in
individuals
but i don't see it happening
collectively in the religions as
systems of distributed cognition so i
place my bet
on the religion that's not a religion
meaning by that
it is a religion that tries to
be other than a religion based on a two
worlds mythology
and is committed to new ecologies and
practices
but also the reinvention of old
ecologies and practices
better said the reinvention of ecologies
and practices both the recovering of the
old and the discovering of the new
right
that's what i mean by the religion
that's not a religion
the reinvention of those ecology of
practices
with with with the best we can draw
from our scientific historic our
scientific
historical and political understanding
of the world
wow that was a masterpiece
there's a lot there's a lot there one
thing
one thing i want to also weave into this
because i think it's
i think it's necessary you know and this
this is
this is still formulating in me but the
importance is becoming more and more
clear
as i was writing that article we spoke
about and even preparing for this
um actually in one ear it seems like
this is necessary and you've mentioned
it several times in this conversation
the profound
importance culture has on
the collective and on the individual and
it's actually
that you know culture is the
culture is the technology that humans
wield right it's this massive sword that
the giant of humanity does stuff with
so it is it is extreme i've written that
in a different article so that wasn't
off the cuff but
yeah like it is a it's a tool basically
it's a tool that
the collective has and that whether we
whether we recognize it or not we can
actually wield it it's not just some
snowball falling down a mountain like we
it's it's a feedback loop
um and so you know what's really
important here
is that culture is being shaped and that
and for a long time throughout history
and arguably still now
religion was a vehicle for the
transformation of culture
right all of them though yes i think
what you've just done is beautiful
it's it's it's it's it's the means by
which we can transform
culture and the distributed cognition
that culture runs on
but also individual cognition but also
you know individual character but also
shared the shared communication between
individuals and the group that affords
distributed cognition
like it transforms all of those like
and and i don't know of any other as i
sort of talked over and i apologize for
that
i would call culture like a tool of
tools um
it's kind of a meta tool yeah and it's a
dynamically self-organizing adaptive
meta tool
that creates all the other tools by
which we adapt uh
chris and i make use of pierce's idea uh
idea that culture is ultimately a
like religion insofar as it wields
culture is ultimately a meta-meeting
system
it's the thing that allows us to
generate all the other individual
meeting systems
and so i don't see anything other than
religion being and thank you for
bringing this point up because it was a
lacuna in my presentation
and it's very astute of you to point to
that
i i don't see anything other than
religion
giving us what we need in order to bring
about the transformation
that will be as comprehensive and as
profound
that it's needed to deal with the
meaning crisis and how the meeting
crisis
interacts and exacerbates the meta
they're just we just we don't have that
that is
the tool of tools for doing that like i
said
i don't think the even though
i i really want to be complimentary even
though i think a lot of the existing
religions are very good tools
i don't think they're the right tool for
this job
and that's why we need the religion
that's not a religion
that's why i often say i i don't
i'm not advocating for the french
revolution i'm not i'm not advocating
primarily for
a political attempt to reorganize
on the system of governance and sort of
the distribution of goods within society
i mean people can vary in what they mean
by the word political that's what i take
to be
uh the meaning of a political revolution
i know there are other people like uh
that that people have a more profound
reading of political
but that's how i'm using it i don't want
something like
the french revolution i want something
like the axial revolution i want
something like what we had when we had
the three r's of the renaissance the
reformation and the scientific
revolution
that you know radically comprehensively
transform
um culture cognition character and
community tasks
in a deeply reciprocal
and profound way that's what we need
right now
something like that yeah and this
actually leads into
something i appreciate that's coming
more and more out of both you and
and jordan hall and some of the thinkers
in this space the idea of stealing the
culture
yeah and that's a very it's a very
important
term because i think there are two
things worth worth
looping in here one is that
a recognition that kind of global or
western culture as it stands right now
is not going in a good direction
for two reasons one you should just
listen to anything daniel
schmachtenberger and jordan hall say
about the meta crisis and how
you know culture has downstreamed that
to to come into being
and also you know we spoke earlier that
like
we are living in a meeting crisis that
has come out of
a culture this culture and it's like
okay so that's probably
not ideal the other very sneaky thing
is that all the perennial problems all
the meaning crisis stuff
it's hard enough to deal with by
yourself and as a community
but it can also be hijacked it can also
be weaponized against you
totally and that is happening in so many
ways
right all the hyper normal stimuli all
the
kind of unsubstantiate unsubstantial
food right and just
like it can all those things difficult
enough when you have a fighting chance
extremely difficult when it gets
weaponized against you for
power and status games right and so it's
there is this
the current culture which and for many
good reasons we can argue
is inadequate to what we need to face
also has a momentum carrying it forward
and people who want to play that game
to basically weaponize it against you
that
the appropriate thing seems to become if
anyone cares about
self others and world and the betterment
of all of them
you actually have to steal the culture
bottom up
right you actually have to straight up
just create a gravity towards you that
is like
this is approachable enough i'm
flourishing enough
it others are flourishing enough we have
community our world is getting better
so much so that they're like i just like
that more like i'm going
i'm going over there and there's a
you know i'm certainly in some some more
spiritual circles now
and there's always this hesitancy in
in people in this space to
basically accumulate status or power or
wealth
right they view them as inherently evil
and it's like
guys like you are the people that should
have this
right or not should but like i would
like to give it more to you than anyone
else
and yet you don't even want to enter the
game at all but it's like
and what i've appreciated most i've
actually seen it in you a lot
jordan hall has always been kind of
subversive but this this warrior energy
of like
yo we are about to do battle we are
going to steal the culture we are going
to rise up and do this
because we need to i need to do it for
myself
my own just existential piece and i need
to do it for the world because that's
what's being called
so um uh actually if i can ramble
one more second on that please this is
beautiful
i think something that doesn't get
spoken enough about as well is this
angry activist
archetype you know something
something like the climate change
activists are a good example
with a lot of anger a lot of justified
anger
things are things are bad but it's
always a yelling at what you don't want
the world to be like
and if you only exist in a space of
not this not this if you actually get
your way
you end up in a void because you haven't
you haven't actually advocated
for anything you're just advocating
against stuff
and so this also why i'm so excited
about the religion that's not a religion
or
you also call it the post-religious
faith which i really like
and this notion of steal the culture is
that it's act
it actually gives people an orient a way
to orient where they're
for something yeah and they can actually
bring that it's tangible it's not just
like
you're doing it wrong you suck go away
it's actually like well let's do
this and you can come up with points and
frameworks and things and that seems
that has by its very nature more ground
to stand on it's actually substantial
i think it has more ground to stand on
thank you for what you just said i
thought that was very well said by the
way
i think it's actually also a better
understanding of what freedom is
which is you know again go back to dirk
brook breakthrough
you you know the advocate you write well
at least a particular version of
advocacy
advocacy can degenerate and so i'll call
it a degenerative form
where as you said the person who's just
angry and what they want is they want
freedom from
acts and that's right but there is no
freedom from without freedom too
the reverse is also the case there's no
freedom too without freedom from
right you have to you have to break the
frame but you also have to make the new
frame
right um and so if people get locked
into anger and if they get locked into
outrage um they have to be careful about
that because
that's a lopsided understanding and
appreciation
of liberation it's only freedom from its
own freedom too
and secondly they have to be careful
that although
they're that they're getting locked into
just the propositional they're getting
locked into what they're saying
and not paying attention to how they're
saying it because
they should understand that the way
modal confusion
is weaponized in our culture especially
on the internet
is by making people trying to create uh
narratives of
of adversary adversarial narratives of
conflict
uh because if i can get people into
deeply opposing groups where they're
deeply angry to each other
that will make them salient like in a
very superficial and fast way
make them very click-baity uh and very
sound bitey
uh and so but you know
a lot of social media the algorithms i
don't think they're
i'm not doing a conspiracy they're not
designed in this set there's not a
social
there's not a cabal of people in the
room smoking cigars planning things
but they they they're they're designed
to enhance sales
uh by basically making people very
impulsive
and oppositional and very superficial
in their appraisal so if i can make you
like get you outraged that is a powerful
machine to benefit um
the way in which i can use you
to sell my products and to use you to
sell my ideas
so one of the concerns i have i
i share with you the concern that
advocacy
when it is reduced to anger
uh is a lopsided understanding of
liberation
and it is also a truncated uh fixation
on
what is being said rather than how
it is being said and people can fail to
realize
that in the very the very speaking
of uh of liberation they can actually be
embodying processes
that are entrapping them and ensnaring
them um
so to give you a concrete example people
confuse
speaking about a diversity of beliefs
with having a belief in diversity right
like
like you know saying that we should have
diversity
is not the same thing as enacting
diversity right
um
and so you have it like and you have to
be careful because one doesn't
automatically guarantee the other
in fact one can actually subvert
the other everybody's got to believe
this it's like okay
but right um so
again i'm not talking i'm not trying to
paint all of protest with the same brush
or anything stupid like that
trying to pick up on a particular
criticism you made and i think it's a
it's an important one
we need to bring back right freedom from
something that is giving us a new frame
as opposed to the one we want to break
and we need to
realize that anger is a very short-term
response to
violation but it doesn't it's not
constructive
you need you and i'm sorry this will
sound happy but you need love
you need love you need love is the
creative
you need love because love is what is
what refrigerants have to argue you need
the positive emotions
the negative emotions like anger and
hate this is
like this is some cock's side they
engender reciprocal narrowing
they remove cognitive flexibility
but love engenders insight and
reciprocal opening
and if you only have this you only have
a reciprocal narrowing of frame breaking
and the having propositions you're never
going to get the reciprocal opening and
the being free
yeah and so i
like i think
we need something i
my model is the model of early
christianity and buddhism
or stoicism three examples
or neoplatonism there's four those are
four i know of deeply
right and what you have is think about
christianity because people
you know you have paul you have other
and you you get all of these communities
and what we have now all of these
communities with
qualities and practices and they start
to network together
and they create a new way of love agape
and a new way and it's not
and it's not just in the head they they
go out and they create
the first real welfare and the first
real you know hospitalization
and the caring of like that agape
actually translates
and what they do and then the roman
empire is up here doing all this crap
and what did they do is they it per they
create all these new ecologies and
practices
these new psycho technologies these new
ways of being
and they steal the culture they steal
the culture
same thing with buddhism same thing with
stone system
to a degree
that will work that's a cultural
revolution
that will work that is what we need
right now that's what's
that it's not just something i'm talking
about like pointing at this is already
happening
all of these communities of practice
they're all they're merging
all over the place all of these
gatherings ecclesia that's what
the church meant ecclesia gatherings all
of these gathering
it's all happening right now it's
already happening
all i want to do is land whatever
talented skill i have
to creating a vocabulary right
it's creating a grammar to exemplifying
ecologies and practices
but teaching people what i can giving
people access to the cog side
so that that stealing of the culture
will take on a life of its own
that's the religion that's not a
religion
yeah yeah that's what we're being called
to do right now
and i just gotta point out it was
amazing that
completely spontaneously and offhand you
proved that dukkha and reciprocal
narrowing is always lurking
because even the people who are fighting
for good
good reasons through anger are still
um that can come up that was
that was actually amazing uh do you have
a few more minutes
we're coming yes on time i'm enjoying
this i do
i i want to say one thing now before
um we pass over this topic um
because i was privileged and that's the
right word
although it's a contended word right now
but i don't mean in the social justice
sense
i was privileged uh to have met
akira the dawn and he's taken right
because why am i talking about this
because i'm talking about the
reinvention of myth
and what he's doing what akira did uh
with the meaning wave of you know steal
the culture
is he's in in the proper sense and i
can't do this
but he can and we and he and i got to
have an excellent discussion about this
creating a new mythos around this
language
this way of thinking this way of being i
mean that the meaning wave was just
wonderful and
it's going to reach people in a way that
all of my lecturing won't
and it's going to give them imagery
and and embodied rhythm and music
and right and and that can be shared
also collectively
that will give them a mythos for this in
a way i can't so i want to i want to
just take this opportunity to once again
thank akira for doing that uh i'm deeply
grateful for that because it exemplifies
a potential that i said needs to be
actualized
and he's actualizing it and he's doing a
really good job of it
yeah shout out to carol the don he is
certainly no stranger to these parts
he's been on the podcast and he actually
came to do a meeting wave set for our uh
we hosted a digital retreat right at the
beginning of covid to kind of give some
people some
space and he came to to mix for us and
yeah just in case that wasn't clear
one of akira's latest songs is steal a
culture
from our man johnny v right here and it
is
it is stunning it is stunning and yeah
actually funny enough that was a perfect
segue because i wanted to lead into the
fact that
you know this has been a pretty serious
conversation right i think justifiably
so like this is important
but that doesn't mean that the doing of
it itself has to
be strenuous and disappointing
and annoying because actually i think
there's a case to make where
if done properly or the most effective
way you could do this
and design these things and discover
these practices
is through things like serious play
flow state and inside cascades and
something like circling and deal logos
so that's kind of the progression i want
to go through you give a
brilliant definition of play that i
think
should be way more known and and
just a reframing of play itself and the
value of it
can you speak to that
um so i mean this this is ultimately
drawn
um it's run from a bunch of work it's
done from sort of the glacier and
linocott
after the point about
this is the hard argument um i've got to
talk out there called why
you know psychological growth impossible
has to do with the idea of aspiration
and transformation
i'm deeply influenced i got to meet her
she's just a wonderful
person ellie pauls she literally wrote
the book transformative experience
uh and i recommend her work always
and get to know laurie's work more but
also i have not met her but her
agnes callard's book aspiration there
this whole idea of aspiration
and and so play
well now that we've got this idea of
uh kinds of knowing let's go back to an
instance
again of where people are caught uh
therapy
people go into therapy with the
propositional knowledge of what they
need to do
right they need they they they they
often know what the problem is
propositionally they can state it
right but but they don't they're stuck
they
they can't get to the self and that
and that agent arena relationship that
they need to be in
in order to be alleviated from the loss
of agency
right that they're suffering that's why
they go into therapy
and so what what does the therapist do
for them
why is it problematic well this goes to
ellie paul's work and she gives a
wonderful
uh sort of uh duncan experiments uh to
get you and understand the difficulties
here
um she says imagine your friends come to
you and they give you just
undeniable evidence that they can do the
following they can turn you into a
vampire
and then she asked should we do it so
how would you do it well how would you
think about it
well here's the problem you could you
have all kinds of propositional
knowledge but notice that that's not the
knowledge you want
you want to know what it's like to be a
vampire you want to know the
perspectival knowing
right and you want to know what's it
like what's the identity like
the agent arena participatory knowing
because your biology and your character
and everything's going to be transformed
and and you can't know that until you go
through that transformation
the problem is if you go through that
transformation you're no longer going to
be a human being
right so you're ignorant you're ignorant
because
this is not about propositions and
probabilities
it's about perspectives and
participation in identities
right you can't you're ignorant you
don't know what it will be like
you don't know what you're missing if
you don't become a vampire but here's
the other thing
you don't know what you're going to lose
when you become a vampire so you're
caught
and this is brian's uh idea right you're
caught between two worlds
yeah right it's in the title of his book
you know education between two worlds
right
you're caught between two worlds so what
do you do
well laurie laurie is really sort of
interested in hammering out that problem
and making people realize
that you can't infer your way through it
right it's not it's not something you
can infer your way through
and if people want a more technical
presentation of that argument look
to that talk i refer to right but
so what do we do well what do you do in
therapy
well you you might say to me well wait
wait this is ridiculous i'm not going to
be a vampire
yeah but you know what you might become
that you're not right now you might
become a parent
and right now you're not a parent and
all your propositional knowledge about
being a parent
isn't the perspectival and participatory
knowing of being a parent and being a
kid
does not give you the perspectival and
participatory knowledge
of being a parent sorry doesn't work
that way
well i'll just become a parent then well
you don't know what you're going to lose
yeah and you say well then i won't do it
ah but then you don't know what you're
missing so what do you do
well what do people do so this is where
this is now
sort of my work and this was influenced
by winnicott
but people get a dog and then they take
family pictures with the dog and they
name the dog like a person
and they let the dog sleep with them and
they often get the dog as a puppy and
they have to raise it
and they what are they doing well
they're actually
enacting a symbol the word symbol on
means to join two things together
they're finding something that's that's
similar enough
to a child that they're getting a
perspectival and participatory
taste but it's not fully a child
and so they can you know they're not
they're not over committed
they're not they haven't passed the
point of no return
right because it's a dog and you know
you can give your dog away and people
don't think you're an immoral
person but if you say you know what this
isn't working with my kid
not my kid or what's wrong with you
right
so that's an example of play we've
reduced play to the sense of
frivolousness but many people
developmental
psychologist developmental biologists
right
point out that what play does is it
allows us to enact
symbolically and i mean symbol in a deep
sense
the perspectival and participatory
aspects of the future self in the future
world
without having stepped out of and so now
i can actually compare them
in play and i and this is serious play
this is not frivolous play this is the
serious play that i engage it
that's what you do in therapy in therapy
you seriously play the therapist often
takes on
the role right of the roles you need
analogous to the pet right so
you need perhaps to engage with serious
play with your
mom the perhaps your mom's dead
that's my case what do i do well the
therapist can take on the role for you
and you can seriously play with that so
that
something that wasn't possible for you
while your mom was alive
but that might be possible you might be
able to go through a process of
transformation
through this serious play so that you
can move to another self
another world that is other than how
you are currently having currently
internalized your mother
and see the world in those terms that it
might be
harming you serious play
is where you enact a symbol
and you bring about anagage a reciprocal
opening
that can draw you in that's what a deuce
means education
to drive can draw you into that other
world
and so serious play requires that we
get into what actor calls the paratellic
mode the meta
motivational modes we have different
ways of framing our level of arousal
so when i when i'm doing something for
the sake of an external
purpose and i'm highly aroused that
means i'm frustrated
i'm not getting my i'm not getting my
goal ah
and so more and more arousal is bad
and then when i get my goal oh i relax
i've achieved my goal and that's that
wonderful relaxing content
but notice and i'm not trying to be
graphic here
that's not sort of your attitude when
you're having like when you're
you know i'll say it this way when
you're making love with somebody
like the arousal is really good right
the excitement
well you don't want it to go on forever
i'm not saying that but now
the point isn't to get to the goal state
and relax afterwards
the point is you're doing something for
its own sake
and therefore the arousal isn't a
frustration at not reaching your goal
the arousal now means an intensification
of your involvement
in the process so that's why love making
is also
serious play because what i'm i'm not
i right we can either do an activity for
the sake of a goal
or we can set up an end state just for
the sake of
creating a play space where we can do
something for its own sake
so when i'm playing i'm doing something
for its own sake
what does that have to do with what i
previously said but i'm in the
paratellic state of playing
i'm trying to not have a goal
i'm trying to become a different person
i'm in the being mode
and i want to be intensely involved with
the process
of becoming itself and so
it it's it's it's a disservice
to play that our culture has reduced it
to frivolous entertainment and not to
think about how we we keep the heritage
in words
of what play how play used to be serious
sp you know you play music
or you go to scene to play hamlet
right that's that's not a those aren't
you know i'm talking about like when you
play
music seriously you're doing it for its
own sake or you're seeing the play for
its own sake
because it's a symbol on an enacted
participatory perspectival
symbol art that can bridge you between
worlds
well that's also the verb in chinese for
tai chi you don't do chai
you don't make tai chi you you play tai
chi
so that's what serious play is and
serious play
has to be the
fundamental mode for
the religion that's not a religion
yeah that was a beautiful tie together
i'm glad your comment about
tai chi playing came up i was going to
bring that up
um yeah the you know going to a symphony
is a beautiful
example of that it's you know the thing
is done for its own sake
yes alan watts has a nice distinction
he's like it's not serious it's sincere
right because it's it's it's not ingest
but it's
it's not getting anywhere yeah you know
the the greatest example being if it was
if the goal of music was to get to the
end of the song eventually people would
just produce
the final symbols at the end
because they and it's like well
obviously that's not true
and then the goal is to get back to
silence
yeah honestly just stay with your
silence well i'd do it in the first
place
and and that driving force has also
expanded on very beautifully in finite
and infinite games
oh i was going to mention cars jazz cars
yeah
yeah beautiful book highly recommended
um i think
part of my criticism
of the axial age mythos
and this is a criticism of plato who i
love deeply and profoundly
um is the understanding of right
relationship and sacredness in terms of
perfection
which are these ideas of completion and
closure
um and i think uh
i've met james and uh we were at a
conference together we both loved each
other's talks
um i hope i'm hoping to talk with him
again perhaps on voices with her reiki
um and and so i think james
given what i've read in uh the religious
case against belief and finite and
infinite games
seeing his presentation i think he would
regard that
that ethos of perfection and closure
and completion and rest somehow the
you know resting is resting in in
you know in immortality or something
like that um i think this is to just
massively miss frame i think it's the
having mode as opposed to the being mode
i think it's trying to uh turn the
infinite
game of religio into a finite game
of sort of metaphysical transportation
or something
um and and even the notion of
you know perfection and immortality
immortality is just really i get that
we're wired to avoid death because we're
autopoetic beings
but the idea of an infinity of my
existence
it strikes me as horrific um because
you know if i was
immortal i would have to be invulnerable
i'd have to be invulnerable
and you know one one of the things that
you know that guy said stock has made
really clear
is you know genuine idea logos
genuine growth it it's inseparably bound
up with vulnerability
you know the the breaking the you have
to break the frame
if you're going to make the new frame
and so if i was invulnerable
i would i would be completely
self-enclosed
i i would not be like and then to extend
that
to extend that disconnection for
infinity that's hell
i don't want that right i i don't want
that
but well you say well i'll make you
involved i'll make you vulnerable for
for an infinite amount of time well
that's horrible too because now i have
an infinite amount of sadness
and disappointment right and pain
like i don't want you know i think what
i have and this is the buddhist notion
of
we're in the right the best place for
enlightenment right
we have better than the gods or the or
the people in the underworld
i think what i have is exactly mortality
allows me vulnerability which affords
real
openness and connection but it is made
livable by the fact that it's finite in
length
and so i think all we've got to get
and and cars emphasizes how much
infinite games require vulnerability
and how they're different from finite
games that are trying to bring about
safety and closure and again see the
having mode
one of the things you have to have is
safety but it's moral confusion to bring
that pursuit
of safety into right relationship with
the sacred because
by turning it into the notion of the
perfect because that's exactly a deep
kind of modal confusion
so i i agree i agree
yeah and it's it's beautiful because
like the these all
these all come together right the the
notion of the infinite game is basically
making and playing a game that the
maximum number of people can play for as
long as possible
yes also game in which the playing of
the game
rewrites the rules by which the game is
played yep
which sounds exactly like designing
a dynamic self-organizing post-religious
faith right those things are those
things are basically
synonymous to me yes i think that's
exactly right
i that's why i want to talk to james
again yeah uh
i think that's i think that's exactly
right
and then i think i think the last the
last points i want to bring up here is
so to actually do this to to design as
it goes you need
a way of surfacing insights
and you need a way of doing that
in a group right because this is this is
communal and this leads to
basically flow state which is
essentially i think
i first heard it uh in in your talk
that it's basically an insight cascade
yeah you use the example of a rock
climber
and then something that looks like and
i've been separate
separate from your discussion of
dialogues i've also been watching
circling and guy thing stock very
closely because that feels
that feels on the level of like a meta
psychotec where it's i can actually
discover and identify
the tools that are needed to it's the
system that builds a system
yeah it's an infinite game exactly right
it's a meta psychotech
the idea that i got from a grateful for
it from
my friend hall um because you need you
need a meta psychotech to
uh to coordinate and curate um
your uh and to create uh your your
ecology and practices and again that's
not something you're going to do
individually you have to do it
in distributed cognition very much um
so yeah the the
things like circling are
because i do i do participant
observation in it as well and i've
gotten into um you know well
he's a good friend of mine guy um
talking to him about it so i got i got
to talk to about creator
uh in depth and i've got to participate
in it um
thank you thanks especially to people
like canada and others
and so i think it's a way of creating a
[Music]
flow state within distributed cognition
yeah
which we come to recover
the serious play of perspectival and
participatory intimacy
i think that's important but i thought
and so
i think so circling is definitely part
of this but
and and and i love him for this guy was
receptive
because guy was ultimately trying to
enact heidi was philosophy
right he was receptive to a criticism a
constructive criticism
and i said because i want to bring and
he does too
and i woke this in him i want to bring
philosophia
the cultivation of wisdom into circling
i want
to get what i see in the platonic
dialogue i see not only philia
that if that perspective of
participatory
right intimacy between the players
of the socratic dialectic
socratic dialogue but i also want the
sophia
i want that that that intimacy awakens
in them
and a fining sense
of an intimacy with what makes all
such dialogues possible the ground of
intelligibility
the ground of virtue right
and so what i've been doing with the
work uh with
guy and with chris and with jordan
both exemplifying and then writing chris
and i are putting together
an anthology right now getting a lot of
these people uh to contribute chapters
on inner and outer dialogues
and you know and peter lindberg's help
and peter i think we're doing another
one tonight at the stoa
beginning to sort of practice this you
know
i'm trying to come up with a psychotech
which i call dialectic
which is a way of scaffolding people
into this process of via logos
which is where you get the phylia of
circling
integrated with the aspiration to sophia
and you get philia sophia and that's
where you get
the individual and collective
transformative love or wisdom that then
gives you the place from which and it's
a self-correcting dynamic
that gives you the place from which
right you can
get guidance in how to curate
create and coordinate an ecology of
practice
and the ecology of practice and the the
dialectic deal logos
are inceptively religioned together they
need each other
if i if i try to do just the dialogue
and the dialectic up here without the
ecology
it's going to degenerate into into just
conversation right having a great
conversation is a good thing
but it's not going to be good but if i
just have the ecology and i don't have
the meta
right psychotech again
my capacity for having you know
situating that ecology into a
a a developmental trajectory of growth
and self-correction is also going to be
seriously truncated
but if i put the two together i get
something better
than i get i get a good stalk that is
greater than the sum of the parts
and so that's what dialectic and deal
logos are
deal logos is a family it's a term for a
family of practices
uh there's there's there's uh what the
uh
for the emerge people thomas and
elizabeth are doing in europe
uh there's what uh there's stuff that a
taylor is doing
uh where he's doing circling and then
he's trying to drop a topic into circle
like so deal logos refers to a family
of these practices in which you engender
flow within distributed cognition but
right but like i say
the interpersonal intimacy
affords it becomes a lens through which
you then try to realize
an inter oncological uh intimacy uh a
transformational
intimacy a serious play with the logos
of being itself or the logos of
intelligibility
um so i
i i think i'm offering dialectic
as something that's trying to make use
of the socratic template
uh mostly that play a little bit also
from the way
jesus uses dialogue uh to to help to be
a midwife to help people
give birth to themselves i tell you this
you must be born again
and socrates says he is also a midwife
that helps people give birth to
themselves
so i'm trying to take a template from
those two sages
and reinvent your
dialectic both the interpersonal
and the intrapersonal aspects of it
that's that's what it is that's what i'm
trying to do and
i think it is the the place where we do
the most important serious play
that is the dynamical ground
for the ecology of practices
yeah and it becomes at least it
in my head it is so important because it
also affords the
reciprocal opening that we've touched on
right
in disclosing myself and my truth to a
group
it gets digested and reflected back to
me which opens me up and together we
and again this has to be a communal
thing right and together we
we ride the the spiral upward because
that's always that always engenders love
by the way remember we talked about not
just anger but love
yeah reciprocal opening this is aaron's
work uh aaron's
last name you know so sort of mutually
accelerating disclosure
is how you fall in love not just erotic
love but also friendship love
right that's how that's how you fall in
love with something and
what i want people to do is of course to
fall in love with each other again by
leah
but i also i want them also to fall in
love with being
and and you know to fall in love with
with
with with with sophia uh again
as well because that's what they need to
overcome the meeting crisis
yeah beautifully said beautifully said
well that was quite the the arc we took
together
um is there anything you want to leave
people with
and he asks that you have anything you'd
like to point anyone towards
um so i mean well obviously i think
people should take a look at awakening
for the meeting crisis
i think they should take a look at
voices with ravinki where i'm doing i'm
doing the participant observation and
the reinvention of dialectic and dear
logos with as many people
of good faith as i can um look for the
new series that's going to
basically take this whole arc and you
know and
right after socrates and view this what
does that what does it mean
to bring back dialectic india logos in
the cultivation of wisdom
um how can we take that ancient
practice of dialectic and put it into
fruitful
dialogue with all these emerging
communities of practice like circling
and
uh you know other things like that so
keep your eye open for after socrates
i'm hoping that that will come out later
this year kobet put a wrench in
production uh and also
look for the book that chris and i are
editing um
the book which is the inner and outer
dialogues which is about all that stuff
you and i were just talking about
uh or and also look for the book that uh
daniel greg and i are writing uh on uh
called the cognitive continuum uh from
insight to enlightenment about
how you you know when you get an insight
cascade you get flow and then
when flow is put deeply into perspective
and participatory
transformation you get higher states of
consciousness and when those higher
states of consciousness are put into
an ecology and practices for addressing
the plenty of problems you can get
enlightenment
and we can go from these being terms
that are wrapped in mystique and
obscurity to being a realizable
continuum
that we can start engaging in right now
right right here right now
so take keep your eye open for all of
those things
beautiful yeah and i'll have links for a
lot of what came up here
any of the videos or series that we
mentioned because
again the same way i started it off like
that was um
that was an extremely pivotal series for
me very important and i think again
very important for humans like just
period
right if you are a human we've addressed
that you are always up against the
perennial problems
and john's work does a great deal
to help give you the cognitive
scaffolding
to address that and build a foundation
for yourself
so with all of that thank you so much
sean this was absolutely beautiful
uh well thank you so much eric i i
really i found that this was uh
true uh dear logos i mean if you can get
to a place
with another person where both people
can get to a place where they couldn't
get to on their own
and so that a deeper religion opens up
between them
then that is we have played the infinite
game
at the logo as well so thank you very
much that happened for me
so thank you very much for that as did
it for me yeah
thank you